Guide to the Advertising Paper Dolls collection, 1894-1980 and undated RL.11589
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Advertising Paper Dolls collection
1894-1980 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11589
1.0 Linear Feet
Collection consists of approximately 400 paper dolls, trade cards, bookmarks and other printed materials that comprised promotional packaging or premium gifts for a variety of products dating from the Victorian era to the 1980s. Dolls depict Mother Goose and other fairy tale and nursery rhyme characters; Victorian men, women and children; animals; occupations; and figures in military, international and ethnic dress. Product classes represented include coffee and other beverages, cotton and linen thread and other sewing supplies, food and patent and nonprescription drugs, Companies represented include A&P, Bendix, Clark's O.N.T., Coca-Cola, Estey Organ, General Mills, Horsman Dolls, J&P Coats, Kellogg, Lion Coffee, McLaughlin Coffee, Morton Salt, Munsingwear, Nestle, Pillsbury, Singer, Western and Southern Life Insurance and Worcester Salt. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Advertising Paper Dolls collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Advertising Ephemera collection
Cause Marketing Forum. Halo Awards records
J. Walter Thompson Company. Diamond Information Center Vertical File
Margaret Fishback papers
Collection Overview
Collection consists of approximately 400 paper dolls, trade cards, bookmarks and other printed materials that comprised promotional packaging or premium gifts for a variety of products dating from the Victorian era to the 1980s. Dolls depict Mother Goose and other fairy tale and nursery rhyme characters; Victorian men, women and children; animals; occupations; and figures in military, international and ethnic dress. Product classes represented include coffee and other beverages, cotton and linen thread and other sewing supplies, food and patent and nonprescription drugs, Companies represented include A&P, Bendix, Clark's O.N.T., Coca-Cola, Estey Organ, General Mills, Horsman Dolls, J&P Coats, Kellogg, Lion Coffee, McLaughlin Coffee, Morton Salt, Munsingwear, Nestle, Pillsbury, Singer, Western and Southern Life Insurance and Worcester Salt. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- Food; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Coca-Cola Company; General Mills, Inc; Morton Salt Company; Nestlé; Pillsbury Flour Mills Company; Kellogg Company; Singer Sewing Machine Company
- Paper Dolls by Company, 1894-1980 and undated; 1
  - Bookseller description, undated (Box 1)
  - A-C, undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Adam's Pepsin Tutti Frutti Gum; Ayer's Sarsaparilla (The House that Jack Built); B&B Shoe Store (Pied Piper cut-out story book); Behr-Manning (Daddy Uses Barney's Sandpaper); Bontex Wash Fabrics (Kiddie Kloth Kids); Boraxine; Coca-Cola; Hoyt's German Cologne
  - Barbour's Irish Flax Threads, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Bendix Radio (Military uniforms), 1940s (Box 1)
  - Blackwell's Durham Tobacco Co. (Fashion Dolls), undated (Box 1)
  - Clark's O.N.T., 1930s and undated (Box 1)
    Includes Dolls of All Nations; Dolls Wedding; Double Dolls/Work and Play
  - Clark's O.N.T.; Cottonlene, 1930s and undated (Box 1)
    Includes Mammas/Babies/Girls/Boys; Minuet Series; Soldier Boy; Dolls With Hats; Cottonlene Shorten Pie Series
  - Corning's Buttercup Ice Cream (Dolls of the Allies), circa 1918 (Box 1)
  - D-F, undated (Box 1)
    Includes Dwight's Flour; Enterprise Coffee (Mother Goose); F.W. Rueckheim
  - Diamond Dye (Wells Richardson), undated (Box 1)
  - Enameline (J.L. Prescott)--Flowers, Ethnic Group; Worcester Salt (Ethnic Group), undated (Box 1)
  - G-L, 1898-1901 and undated (Box 1)
    Includes Great Atlantic & Pacfic Tea Company (Grandmother's Afternoon Tea); Happy Family Candy (4 Mammas/Babies/Girls/Boys); Honey Nut Cheerios (Annette); Horsman Dollies; KC Baking Powder (Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition 1898); Burnham Company (Burnham Hasty Jellycon); Leinbach (Soldier Doll cards)
  - J&P Coats, undated (Box 1)
    Includes 3-Sided Dolls; Dolls with Hats
  - Lion Coffee, undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Includes Children's Dolls with Stories; Doll House; Nursery Rhymes; Occupations; Riding Brownies; Standing Brownies
  - M, 1903-1980 and undated (Box 2)
    Includes Maypole soap; Reid, Murdock Baking Powder (Javanese Coffee Dolls); Gronseth & Olsen's Viking Coffee; McKinney's Blue Ribbon Bread; Cordova Coffee; Mellin's Food; Hulman Crystal Coffee; Minneapolis Garments (Miss Minneapolis); Morton Salt (Umbrella Girl); Munsingwear (Munsingwear Family; Miss Molly Munsing)
  - N-O, undated (Box 2)
    Includes Nahn Bakery (Animals); Nestle (France, in French); New England Condensed Mince Meat (Fairy's Children Who Ate the Fairy Pie); Oxford Biscuits (Family; Denmark, in Danish)
  - None Such New England Mince Meat (International Dolls), undated (Box 3)
  - P-T, 1917-1962 and undated (Box 3)
    Includes Panama Coffee (8 Boys and Girls); Pearline (Triplets); Pillsbury; Pozzonis (Bookmark); Estey Organ (Dolls of America and Her New Possessions); Somervilles Pepsin Gum (Spaniard); Washington Crisps (Mother Gooseland); Jacob Hoffman Brewery; Stollwerck's Breakfast Cocoa (Fairy Tale Series); Tonette (Hairbow Set); Twinkles (Dotty Dean Doll)
  - W, undated (Box 3)
    Includes W.K. Kellogg; Warner's Brassieres (Dolly's Trunk); Western & Southern Life Insurance; Beecham's Pills (Fairy tale characters); Merrick's Spool Cotton (Head and Shoulder Dolls); Willimantic Thread Co. (Cut-out boy and girl dolls); Singer Sewing Machine (Cut-out female doll)
  - W.F. McLaughlin Company (Coffee), 1894-1896 and undated; 5 folders (Box 3)
    Includes 4 Mammas/Babies/Girls/Boys; 8 Boys and Girls; 12 Girls 4 Boys; 16 Interchangeable Dolls; 16 Young Ladies; 23 Stand-Up Set; Activity Set; Cape Series; Queens and Nursery Rhymes; Standing Animals with Costumes; Victorian Ladies and Gentlemen; also Dr. Pierce's Favorite Prescription for Weak Women; Kickapoo Indian Pills and Indian Salve; Our Little Girl Chewing Gum